so this is uh these
suten is samyuttanika called the sun's
flesh and this is about the
and this is about the
four kinds of nutrients for the
maintenance of being
that have a
from the maintenance of beings that have
already come to be and for the
assistance of those about to come to
being the last thing is for the maintenance of
the last thing is for the maintenance of
being
the maintenance of your being yeah
but a maintenance of baba
yeah so what for
so what for
the nutriment
of
food of consuming consumable food edible
food gross or subtle
gross or subtle
second is
contact passer
passer
third is mental
intention and fourth is consciousness
and fourth is consciousness
these are the four kinds of nutrients
so in terms of the first
nutrient of
edible food
how should it be seen
and there's a simile
it's given
[Music] suppose a couple
suppose a couple
husband and wife had taken limited
provisions and were traveling through a
desert they had with them their only son dear
they had with them their only son dear
and beloved then in the middle of the
desert their limited provisions would be
used up and exhausted
while the rest of the desert remains to
be crossed
the husband and wife would think
our limit limited provisions have been
used up and exhausted
while the rest of this desert remains to
be crossed
let us kill our only son dear and
beloved and prepare dried meat by eating
our son's flesh we can cross the rest of
this desert
let us all not perish
some practical thing in there so it says
then because the husband and wife would
kill their son
who they loved
prepare dried meat and by eating their
son's flesh they would cross the rest of
the desert
but while they are eating their son's
flesh they would cry and become
distraught where are you our only son where are you
where are you our only son where are you
our only son what do you think because
would they eat that food for jesus
for the sake of physical beauty and
attractiveness no
no
would they eat the food for the sake of
crossing the desert yes
it is in such a way because that i say
that the nutriment
of edible food should be seen
when that
nutriment of food is fully understood
lust for the five chords of central
pleasure he's fully understood
when that's fully understood
there is no fetter bound by which a
noble disciple can japan might return to
this world yeah
yeah so there you go complete this
passion towards food
how by developing the context that
will prevent you
from having any passion towards it
so that's the similarity the
similarities not just uh
yeah i don't know some poetic
shocking emphasis or like how you should
know it's like imagine
eating your own child how would that
feel for survival
well now
now
take that context
and apply to any food you eat
that's how it should feel
that's where you need to need to sustain
why because
the mind will completely turn away from
any enjoyment amusement any any any lust
enjoyment amusement any any any lust
towards
edible food edible nutrient
which in return will completely remove
any attachment and desire towards the
five chords of central pleasure
because that's what it all comes down to
you wouldn't consumption of pleasure you
wouldn't be absorbed into that food lost
oh no no
not just not just you wouldn't be lost
you would you would eat only to the
point of like survival you wouldn't eat
for the sake of eating for the sake of
chewing for the sake of consuming for
the sake of enjoying you would only have
one goal in your mind so
so
whenever you eat whenever you're putting
something in your mouth
that you are consuming
always bring that context up
and that even before you're eating
actually when you're about to eat bring
that context up and then you'll see
whether you need to eat
and how much
and whether
well if there is any passion towards
what you're eating
well it won't be there
if you sustain this context the passion
cannot survive in that environment
but it's not
yes it's lovely food that i'm about to
eat it doesn't matter
who knows maybe even the boy tasted
really nice
like in terms of the actual taste but it
doesn't mean that at any given time
mother and father could have enjoyed it
so it's not that the mouth won't
perceive agreeability of the texture or
food but
but
that's completely not the basis for
passion loss of context is the basis for passion
loss of context is the basis for passion
for the availability of the taste and so
i'm eating
i'm putting this food in my mouth for
this body
to continue
yeah so why
why do you need the body to continue
well there's that so i can practice the
whole life right so what does that
practice a whole life entail do you know
what the practice is or is this just the
idea of
i'm practicing by you know
thinking about practice
so do you see what the practice is
if the answer is no well you should
really see what the practice is because
none of this then applies to you until
then
so doing something about the dhamma does
not constitute practicing the holy life
does not even cause you practicing the
dharma so i would think that's the way i'm
so i would think that's the way i'm
eating as well
no i wouldn't worry about the way you're
eating if the context is there don't matter
if the context is there don't matter
which way you're eating
yeah i'm not talking like slow like
slowly what [Music]
[Music]
the context of this is going inside the
body for the body
for the body
not for all right right right yeah yeah
sure join me it's not going in
but all of that is kind of
psychologizing now that
like all of those
insights and the way you can describe it
are fine
if the context is there
the context of eating for the right
reason only not too much not too little
not overthinking it certainly not giving
in to the enjoyment craving and kind of
emotional dependence on agreeable food
but if their context is not there
then yeah i mean you can analyze it and you
yeah i mean you can analyze it and you
can visualize it and you can contemplate
how just in the body and stuff but
fundamentally the passion is still there
so that's why the drastic simulator that
it would have gave
not about you know imagine the body is
not yours and you're providing food for
it and so on
all that's true
but it won't work because the lust is
you know
rooted deeper than that
so what will work is when you don't want
to eat it but you have to
and what will work even more when you
don't want to eat it but you have to and
what you have to eat is what was dearest
to you that's not meant to be eaten
so then it's like there's no
not a grain of your you know of your
being would want to be eating it it will
need it just to survive purely
same like you know the simile of the
charcoal pit with burning embers and two
men come and want a dragon throw you in
and then your mind will want to be
anywhere else except there he would
intention would go in any direction
except to the pit so why can't i just
enjoy my food
why can't i just eat it because it
doesn't belong to you
my
food yeah your body doesn't go out there
so how can you eat the food as if it's
yours [Music]
[Music]
i mean you can eat it if you want you
can enjoy it if you want
it's not like why can't i yes you can
but then you have to suffer the
consequences in the same sense a fish suffer
in the same sense a fish suffer
consequences when he eats the food that
he whatever
unwaryly that the the fisherman puts on
a bait
fish enjoys it as a result it gets
hooked so it's not a
so it's not a
that we are outlining some moral law
here that you must hate your food and
eat it like if it's your only child do
what you like eat and enjoy if you want
to
but what's the danger well exactly
what's the danger well exactly
there is danger is the danger well i'm
not going to tell you
see it for yourself
you already know that there is some
danger that's the point
because why why would otherwise then
life and food
and food
and uh and other codes of central
pleasure be be so
bent on
pleasure and ignoring pain and
outrunning pain and and sort of um
being completely
maintaining the certain level of
unawareness of your own situation why do
people don't like to think about the
illness their own illness or even illness for
their own illness or even illness for
people that are dear to them
mortality aging why why is that oh so there must
aging why why is that oh so there must
be something there that people don't
want to admit
well chasing pleasure or food or
otherwise is tied to that
so if you stop and think about it you
would see that maybe you know yeah
i could enjoy food i could enjoy the
senses but what if there is a catch
there and again even the most untrained mind
and again even the most untrained mind
can see
like what we said in previous talks
even if you don't know anything about a
dharma no values or precepts or whatever
else everybody at some point in their life
everybody at some point in their life
sooner or later do get a recognition of
what's the point like chasing the
desires again food or otherwise
only results in a very very temporary
satisfaction and it's not even satisfaction it's more
and it's not even satisfaction it's more
like forgetting about the pressure
during it
during or a little bit out doesn't
matter the point is and then again
and then again
and then again so you already kind of
have a very good inkling that
oh so there is no end to this
and i'm kind of enslaved by it and
that's not a good position to be in
but hey i'll forget about that because
i'll chase the next desire and next
desire and next desire
and that's how people go through life
so yes you can do that nobody says you
shouldn't but again
but again
they're the consequences and you will
have to pay the price for it
price of eating consuming and taking all
these things up that don't belong to you
then when in the end the bill comes
and you realize oh now i have to pay for
all of that i thought it was mine i
thought i was the owner i thought it was
free but it's not
but it's not
if it were free it wouldn't be
pressuring you so much
he wouldn't be enticing you so much he
wouldn't be trapping you so much you
wouldn't be baiting you so much
it's always a catch
so when lust for the five chords of
central pleasure is fully understood
there is no fatter bound by which the
noble cycle might come back to this
world yeah so full understanding fully
understanding that
um lust in
assumptions in regard to the solid food
you will fully understand and remove the
ownership of the physical body that
depends on the solid food
it won't be taken as yours anymore by
fully understanding the body as it would
have said in another suture but fully
understanding but by being fully
developed in regard to your own body
you will fully overcome the the last
towards the five chords of central
pleasures so therefore by fully understanding the
so therefore by fully understanding the
solid food you will fully understand the
five chords the same pleasure
the second nutrient
how big is should the nutriment
of contact pasta be seen
suppose there is a flayed cow
a cow with no skin on it
if she stands exposed to a wall the
creature's dwelling in the wall would
nibble at her
if she stands exposed to a tree the
creatures dwelling in the tree would
bite at her
if she stands exposed to water the
creatures dwelling in the water would
bite at her
if she stands exposed to the open air
the creatures drowning in the open air
would bite at her
whatever that
whatever that flake car stands exposed
to
the creatures dwelling there would
nibble at her
yeah that's why i like to translate
pasta contact as pressure
it's not it's not a impersonal
mechanical or biological contact
like it's the mental pressure
passes the pressure to act on account of
what you felt
and that's exactly how how the car is
feeling it's not just oh yes this is the
and so whatever insects are just
anatomically chewing on my flesh like as
a matter of fact no it's pressure it's
harassed it's annoyed it's it's attacked
it's devoured
so it's uncomfortable
the contact is uncomfortable
so do you regard contact pasta as
uncomfortable or do you not even see it
or do you not even see it
as a pressure at all
so in that case your understanding or
your idea of pasta is very inaccurate
and usually it is very inaccurate people
usually think
due to the you know the whole commentary
on this misrepresentation
like it's like this this just
like a physical coming of the senses and
then poof the result of this is the
sight and the sound
as if like you know nothing to do with
me and i'm not responsible for it no no
pasa is basically yes having eyes and
sights but being pressured on account of
what's felt in regard to that that's
what pasa is
so in other words if people want to
understand parser want to understand the
situation of that cow
find things within your mind where you're
things within your mind where you're
emotionally pressured on account of
anything side sounds multi-touch thought
doesn't matter
if there is a pressure there if there is
a discomfort there that's where passes
and that's what needs to be understood
not psychologically or anatomically
explained in terms of sense organs and
what like whatever else biology and so
on
that's not the pasta
because it makes no difference so
imagine the cow being divided by the insects and
the cow being divided by the insects and
you're telling it oh no see this is
what's happening to you okay yeah but
i'm still pressured i still suffer so
that knowledge of
explanation of the contact is not free
me from this discomfort thus it's not
the knowledge because if the knowledge
truly pertains to the nature of that
phenomena it would be resulting in
freedom from suffering
as the suitors would say so this full
understanding of contact results in you
being free from the pressure
yes it is it is in such a way because as
i say nutrient of concert to contact
should be seen yeah when the nutrient
content is fully understood the three
kinds of feeling are fully understood
exactly because that's where the pressure is
because that's where the pressure is
it's where the feeling is
so fully understand
the nature pressure
you have fully uprooted
any resistance or welcoming towards
feelings respective feelings
so you're fully you're completely free
from claiming in other words
but understanding yeah by understanding
the pressure in regard to the currently
enduring feeling
not by explaining it
but by this understanding its nature
that will kind of you know
will kind of you know
result
in complete freedom from it
so you subject it
yeah so you could you could look include
but first you need to feel the pressure
and you can start this abstract
questioning and self-interrogation but
you first need to feel the pressure
account of that whatever feelings
present there because it's there
some pressure always has to be there you
can't like oh now in at the moment i'm
in between the contacts
i'm in limbo no there's always something
felt which means there's always
something pressuring you
big or small doesn't matter pressure is
there so first you need to stop acting out of
so first you need to stop acting out of
that pressure habitually
then allow the feeling to endure
then the phenomenon of pressure that
manifests in regard to that
then you can start interrogating the
properties of it
which is what we said in previous talk
in itself the pressure to act
is is enough
in itself it does not imply any action
depression yeah itch does not imply a
scratch you assume a scratch because you
don't want the itch
you assume the act out of pressure to
relieve the pressure because you don't
want the pressure
if you remove the gratuitous resistance
to the pressure in itself pressure is
just the pressure thus it's not
pressuring you
[Music] anymore but for that the mind needs to
anymore but for that the mind needs to
be developed
in order to see that without giving in
to that subtle i don't want this or i
want this
but the only way to develop it is to
endure it sufficiently enough not to
find the right second or moment in
between to catch it no
how do you become imperturbable by
practicing not being perturbed
by enduring
you stop moving
and the pressure to move will fade away
because you're not feeding it anymore
but not
not
not to practice sympathetic and not
moving in regard to everything and
nothing no
no
in regard to the pressure
that's there on account of what you're
currently feeling
so that's where you had these misguided
ascetic practices
where people endured so much yet
remained equally ignorant
because they moved
well exactly they were not moving on the
level that it didn't matter whether you
move or not but they were moving on the
level where it mattered
so
you need to find that level of present
enduring feeling and don't move there
everything else is fine everything else
is second to it everything else will
fall in place if you approve the craving
on the level where it matters
so and the third nutrient
mental intention mental position
intention mental position
suppose there is a charcoal pit deeper
than a man's height filled with glowing
coals with flame or smoke
a man would come along wanting to live
not wanting to die
desiring happiness and averse to
suffering then two strong men
would grab him by both arms and drag him
towards the charcoal pit
the man's intention
collision would be
to get far away his longing would be to
get far away
his wish would be to get far away from
that from the charcoal pit for what
reason because he knows i will fall into
this charcoal pit and on account of that
i will be death or deadly suffering
so it is in such a way that because that
i say the nutrient of mental intention
should be seen
when that
mental intention is fully understood
the three kinds of craving are fully
understood
so mental intention should be seen yeah
so what would what would practically
what would
what would be a practical example of
mental intention
i want to go what i want
that's it
one thing
so i desire i want i want this i don't
want that
now you can't like oh okay i don't want i
you can't like oh okay i don't want i
don't want my wanting but i don't want
anything because that's not what you
want [Music]
[Music]
so you can't just want your way out of
your desire but
but
it is the attitude of wanting so then
what do you want
are those wants of yours
still pertaining to the five codes of
central pleasure one way or the other
subtle or close
are they still pertaining to you know
gratuitous assumption of safety in this
world through this assumption of ownership
through this assumption of ownership
my own sense of self
are those ones still revolving around
those things
that's what needs to change
that's what the buddha says you know you
replace the joys
of central life with the joys of
renunciate life
of a life that says no to centrality
you replace
the the miseries the suffering
the miseries the suffering
of the central life with the suffering
of the renunciant life because it's
better so it's not optional
so it's not optional
experiencing joys
and miseries or like well for as long as
you have the body
but what's optional is
um
what joys and miseries will be
experienced whether they're going to be
pure or not whether they're going to be
causing more attachment or not whether
they're going to be causing more
infatuation and last or not
so replace
the central ones with their enunciate
ones and sustain that and there will be no
and sustain that and there will be no
problem normal problems for you
so
you can want everywhere else
you can want anything else except the
five cause of central pleasures for
example that's it so stay in that context and
that's it so stay in that context and
you will overcome lust or essentiality
because you're not feeding it anymore
through gratuitous sustaining of one
wanting it valuing it
anyway except that anywhere except that
yeah yeah so that's you know the joys of
seclusion used to replace the joys of a household
used to replace the joys of a household
life joys of
pains of seclusion pains of renunciation
replace the pains of a household life
which are far worse
far more burdening and far more like um
carrying like much much further reaching
consequences things you do on account of sensuality
things you do on account of sensuality
pertain that you know consequences come
like in lives to come not just not just
in this one
but pains of seclusion that enunciation
pretty much ends there
because there's nothing done on account
of it
no other people affected by it so it's
not does not carry the same significance
and yet you used it to now replace all
this other burden that would have
otherwise caused you so much more hassle
so that's the mental wanting it's not
like that you cannot have it
but you should certainly make sure that
none of it is rooted
in the domain of the senses
in the domain of
as i said ownership and like
is your wanting based
on just pleasure
more pleasure
gratuitous sense of safety or is your
wanting based on practicality for
example practicality is suitable for practice
practicality is suitable for practice
enough food enough food enough shelter
enough ropes or clothes
enough means to to live by or is your
wanting based on much more than that
so it's replacing the bad wanting with
good wanting let's say like that
in simple terms
and then sustaining
the the good wanting until you can
completely disown even that
so why is it called nutrient
well because your sense of self
your being
all of your assumptions are fed by it
depend on it sustained by it that's what
you're saying sustaining it it sustains
it
whether you want it or not through
acting you are feeding it
so you it's a it's a direct nutrient
for for power for ego for conceit for
for power for ego for conceit for
everything for ownership
vicious circle yeah
[Music] so food will maintain
so food will maintain
that power
food is well eating them eating well see
four types of nutriment but what's
what's in common to all those nutrients
there are nutriments for power and for
your sense of self
when you take them wrongly
so see the one who is free from nutrient
to food and arahant
doesn't stop eating food
but eating food ceases to be the
nutriment for his being because he's
eating it like his dead child that he
just killed in order to survive
so there is no wanting anymore
no desire no lust in regard to the
nutrient for food thus it has ceased to
be the nutrient
nutrient for baba neutra meant for his
being and misconceptions
and then contact for him
personally there is no pressure exactly
pressure again it was your attitude
as i said itch is enough in itself
does not require a scratch nor even
imply but there's still an itch there is
still an itch but it does not pressure
towards scratching
is just an edge
so when you are not developed in regard
to the itch
your mind cannot resist the thoughts
the delight the pressure the possibility
of scratch
remove the itch
but agent itself is self-sufficient it's
enough in each there's just the edge
and if you start seeing it like that
you will not be pressured
to scratch it
so the pressure for scratching it will
fade away
and then those intentions that one thing
won't be
feeding that bother either exactly exactly yeah
that bother either exactly exactly yeah
so that's why you know that they would
have said you know passer
contact cannot contact the groundless
one the one that has no ground for that
pressure to land
no ownership no no delight no lust in
those thoughts of what if i only scratch
it none of that he completely disowned
thus the thoughts of scratching
do not pressure him anymore
so the itch is there the thoughts of
scratching might be there but there is
no more pressure to scratch
and then even the thoughts of scratching
will fade away
and then again in the edge there's just
ditch in the scene there's just the
scene in the herd it's just the herd and
so on
it's no longer being fueled but no
longer yeah nutrients yeah
yeah nutrients yeah
and same with the wanting and the
and the
the last one
number four
and how should the nutrient
consciousness be seen
suppose they were
they were to arrest a criminal and bring
him before the king saying
sire this man is a criminal impose on
him whatever punishment you wish
the king says to them go man in the
morning and strike this man with a
hundred spears
in the morning they strike him with a
hundred spears then at noon the king
asks men how's that man
men how's that man
still alive sire
then go at noon strike him
with a hundred spears
at noon they're striking with a hundred
spears then then in the evening the king
asks men how's that man
men how's that man
still alive sire
then go and in the evening strike him
with 100 spears in the evening they're
striking with 100 spears
what do you think because would that man
be struck with 300 spears
being struck with 300 spears experience
pain and displeasure on that account
very well so even if he were struck with
one spear he would experience pain and
displeasure on that account not a speak
of 300 spears
it is in such a way because that i say
the nutriment
consciousness should be seen
when that is fully understood name and
form is fully understood
the all has been fully understood
what's the same
yeah so what's the property of
consciousness practically speaking
the property of consciousness yeah what
is it well presence well presence
life
lead what do all those things have in
common
even even the etymology of consciousness
cognizing so they're cognized that's it
so they're cognized that's it
so it's it's the subtlest obviously it's
the subtlest nutriment
you know see understanding the nutrient
food you'll be an origami but there will
you'll be an origami but there will
still be you know your like subtler
forms of lust and aversion for being for
non-being and so on
conceit would be left
and the
[Music] consciousness is pretty much if if the
consciousness is pretty much if if the
subtlest form the the subtlest type of
nutrient because it's on the level of
just mere cognizing of things
but are you cognizing those things with
implication for me
mine i am
i am
or are you cognizing those things as not
for me not mine not i am
as the buddha encouraged
the the noble disciples to to regard
everything not for me not mine not i am
so anything notice
is it cognized with the implication for
me i am in regard to this
as malaparia says
conceive in apart from
mine
or are you recognizing it without it
without all of that
why the symbol of spears why is it
well because it's so subtle
that you can't you know you can't
recognize your cognizing correctly
because any form of cognizing already
carries that conceit for me and mine
so the only way to penetrate through
that is to again same like the similar
of eating your own child
to regard it as the most perilous thing
in the world
that's that must not be wanted and then
sustain that context
as the framework for any cognizing that
arises until that cognizing is purified
but you can't do it on the level of
cognizing it's just too subtle
and your tool for doing it is cognizing
so your tools are corrupted already
but what you can do is develop the
framework of
okay so any form of cognition
any situation i become self-aware in
is like being struck with a spear
pedal pain possibility of death
so what next nothing sustain that
attitude there will be no more basis for
passion and loss to endure and to to
proliferate so they will have to like that heating
so they will have to like that heating
up the pan as the buddha gave that
simile when the pan is really hot even if you
when the pan is really hot even if you
throw a lot of water on it it will
evaporate instantly
so that that's how you get rid of the
conceit that that's affecting your
recognizing by providing a hot pan for it
by providing a hot pan for it
that context
exactly context is the hot pan yeah
the context of not mine so whatever you
experience well not just not mine that's
again to abstract the context of
this is my death
this is a spear
that i might die as a result of and
again that's the contemplation of death
if your context of death is in regard to
even in breath or out breath there
unchanged sustaining the context yeah
all the lust passion conceit will have
to evaporate
from your experience cannot stay there
because the context is just frying it
all up especially especially
dispassioning
so whatever is presence present whatever
i experience a sight
sound well it's not even you don't want to
well it's not even you don't want to
start on that particular level of
satisface psp no no cognizing so
what is your current situation what is
your current state of mind what is a
currently enduring feeling what's your
current body posture all this level all
this form of recognizing
so on that general level at peripheral
level not uncognizing the table
recognizing the book i'm cognizing the
phone i'm good no
i'm cognizing my current situation of
such and such feeling enduring and i'm
sitting here that's despair my the
broadest context i can find is despair
and that's how you broaden even that
context broaden in a sense of
broaden in a sense of
um
[Music] develop it further so it becomes even
develop it further so it becomes even
more unsuitable for passion
for carelessness for ownership
and if it's unpleasant
it's only unpleasant because of your
ownership that's there
if there is no ownership it would not be
unpleasant same like when you put you know
same like when you put you know
disinfecting alcohol on your skin unless
your skin is broken
and infected it won't hurt
so it hurts only because there is a
wound but if you're really unwise you would
but if you're really unwise you would
think oh no it hurts because of alcohol
thus i won't put the disinfectant on
i'll just let the wound stay because i
don't want the hurt
so when you develop the context and it
hurts it hurts because there is a wound which
it hurts because there is a wound which
means if the wound heals it will stop
hurting without you needing to abandon
the context so then
so then
so it says yeah
when consciousness fully understood name
and form is fully understood anything
that can manifest however subtle name
and form another suitable called the all
anything that can be described or
designated thought of remembered planned
doesn't matter past few to present
has to be within name and form so means
if you fully
uh developed the context in regard to
this passion towards cognizing of any
kind anything that can be cognized
anything that can be cognized
will be free from passion you will be
fully understood
name and form
which is anything that can be recognized
so there's really nothing left to do
then no more conceit no more basis frequency
no more conceit no more basis frequency
to last so that's the complete
arrangement no matter what is cognizable it doesn't
no matter what is cognizable it doesn't
matter coconuts is just recognized